---
layout: nil
title : Jan Vanhove - new publications
---
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Jan Vanhove: latest publications</title>
 <link href="http://janhove.github.io/paperfeed.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://janhove.github.io/"/>
 <updated>{{ site.time | date_to_xmlschema }}</updated>
 <id>http://janhove.github.io/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Jan Vanhove</name>
   <email>jan.vanhove@unifr.ch</email>
 </author>
 
<entry>
	<title>New article - The influence of Standard and substandard Dutch on gender assignment in second language German</title>
	<link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
	<updated>2017-02-20T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#grammaticalgender</id>
	<content type ="html">This study investigated how standard and substandard varieties of first language (L1) Dutch affect grammatical gender assignments to nouns in second language (L2) German. While German distinguishes between masculine, feminine, and neuter gender, the masculine–feminine distinction has nearly disappeared in Standard Dutch. Many substandard Belgian Dutch varieties, however, still mark this distinction, making them more akin to German than Standard Dutch in this respect. Seventy-one Belgian and 104 Netherlandic speakers of Dutch with varying levels of German proficiency assigned gender-marked German articles to German nouns with Dutch cognates; these gender assignments were then compared to the cognates’ gender in the standard and substandard L1 varieties. While the gender assignments of both Belgian and Dutch participants were strongly influenced by the cognates’ Standard Dutch gender, the Belgians’ responses showed, at best, weak traces of the masculine–feminine distinction in substandard Belgian Dutch. Possible reasons for this weak substandard variety influence are discussed.</content>
</entry>
 
<entry>
	<title>New article - Interactions between formal distance and participant-related variables in receptive multilingualism</title>
	<link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
	<updated>2017-01-30T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#interactions</id>
	<content type ="html">
</content>
</entry>
 
<entry>
	<title>New article - Age of second-language acquisition: Critical periods and social concerns.</title>
	<link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
	<updated>2016-08-30T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#critPeriod</id>
	<content type ="html">
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
	<title>New article - Item-related determinants of cognate guessing in multilinguals</title>
	<link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
	<updated>2015-10-28T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#itemdets</id>
	<content type ="html">
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
	<title>New booklet - Statistische Grundlagen: eine Einführung mit Beispielen aus der Sprachforschung</title>
	<link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
	<updated>2015-05-29T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#statcourse</id>
	<content type ="html">
Dieses Skript ist eine Einführung in die Analyse quantitativer Daten, die sich an erster Stelle an Forscherinnen und Forscher im Bereich der angewandten Linguistik richtet.
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
	<title>New article - Analyzing randomized controlled interventions: Three notes for applied linguists</title>
	<link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
	<updated>2015-03-10T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#ssllt2015</id>
	<content type ="html">
I discuss three common practices that obfuscate or invalidate the statistical analysis of randomized controlled interventions in applied linguistics. These are (a) checking whether randomization produced groups that are balanced on a number of possibly relevant covariates, (b) using repeated measures ANOVA to analyze pretest-posttest designs, and (c) using traditional significance tests to analyze interventions in which whole groups were assigned to the conditions (cluster randomization). 

The first practice is labeled superfluous, and taking full advantage of important covariates regardless of balance is recommended. The second is needlessly complicated, and analysis of covariance is recommended as a more powerful alternative. The third produces dramatic inferential errors, which are largely, though not entirely, avoided when mixed-effects modeling is used. 

This discussion is geared towards applied linguists who need to design, analyze, or assess intervention studies or other randomized controlled trials. Statistical formalism is kept to a minimum throughout.
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
	<title>New article - The early learning of interlingual correspondence rules in receptive multilingualism </title>
	<link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
	<updated>2015-03-10T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#ijb2015</id>
	<content type ="html">
Aims and objectives: This article investigates whether learners are able to quickly discover simple, systematic graphemic correspondence rules between their L1 and an unknown but closely related language in a setting of receptive multilingualism.

Design: Eighty L1 German speakers participated in a translation task with written Dutch words, most of which had a German cognate. In the first part of the translation task, participants were shown 48 Dutch words, among which either 10 cognates containing the digraph ‹oe› (always corresponding to a German word with ‹u›) or 10 cognates with the digraph ‹ij› (corresponding to German ‹ei›). During this part, participants were given feedback in the form of the correct translation. In the second (feedback-free) part of the task, participants were shown another 150 Dutch words, among which 21 cognates with ‹oe› and 21 cognates with ‹ij›.

Data and analysis: The participants’ German translations of ‹oe› and ‹ij› cognates in the second part were coded for the presence of ‹u› and ‹ei›, respectively. The data were then analyzed in generalized linear mixed models. Data and R code are available online.

Findings: Participants who encountered ‹oe› or ‹ij› cognates in the first part were more likely to translate ‹oe› or ‹ij› cognates using German words containing ‹u› or ‹ei›, respectively, in the second part compared to their respective controls, suggesting that correspondence rule learning had taken place. Learning effects during the second part, i.e. in the absence of explicit feedback, were more modest.

Originality: This study provides the first direct experimental evidence of interlingual correspondence rule learning during a receptive multilingualism task.

Significance: These findings pave the way towards investigations of the learning of more complex, less systematic correspondence rules that are nonetheless of great importance in receptive multilingualism.
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
	<title>New article - The lifespan development of cognate guessing skills in an unknown related language</title>
	<link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
	<updated>2015-03-04T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
	<id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#iral</id>
	<content type ="html">This study investigates the lifespan development of the ability to correctly guess the meaning of foreign-language words with known translation-equivalent cognates. It also aims to identify the cognitive and linguistic factors driving this development. To this end, 159 German-speaking Swiss participants aged 10 to 86 were asked to translate 45 written and 45 spoken isolated Swedish words with German, English or French cognates. In addition, they were administered an English language test, a German vocabulary test as well as fluid intelligence and working memory tests. Cognate guessing skills were found to improve into young adulthood, but whereas they show additional increases in the written modality throughout adulthood, they start to decrease from age 50 onwards for spoken stimuli. Congruently with these findings, L1 vocabulary knowledge is a stronger predictor of written cognate guessing success, whereas fluid intelligence is the most important predictor in the spoken modality. Raw data and computer code used for the analyses are freely available online.</content>
</entry>

 <entry>
   <title>New article - Factoren bij het herkennen van cognaten in
onbekende talen: algemeen of taalspecifiek?</title>
   <link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
   <updated>2014-08-02T22:30:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://homeweb.unifr.ch/VanhoveJ/Pub/papers/Cog4Talen/FactorenCognaatherkenning.pdf</id>
   <content type="html">The correct recognition of cognate relationships is a precondition for receptive
multilingualism within language families. Several item- and participant-related
factors have been identified that affect the probability with which readers
and listeners correctly recognise and translate cognates in an unknown but
genealogically related foreign language. Most of the relevant findings, however, are based on tasks featuring cognates in only one unknown language,
leaving open the possibility that these factors play a (somewhat) different
role depending on the specific stimulus language. To address this issue, 98
German-speaking participants were asked to translate 181 written cognates
from four Germanic languages (Danish, Dutch, Frisian and Swedish). The effects
of stimulus similarity to known (L1, L2, ..., Ln) cognates, cognate frequency
and the participants’ foreign language skills on translation accuracy were
assessed and found not to vary substantially between stimulus languages. This
indicates that the validity of studies on cognate recognition extends beyond
the language from which the stimuli were sampled. Secondary findings are
discussed as well.</content>
 </entry>
 
  <entry>
   <title>New article - Entre jeunes barbes et vieux de la vieille. Usages du répertoire plurilingue dans une tâche d'intercompréhension à travers les âges.</title>
   <link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
   <updated>2014-07-01T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#valsasla</id>
   <content type="html">In this article, we discuss a receptive multilingualism task administered to German-speaking Swiss
participants aged between 10 and 86 years. 159 participants were presented with 90 isolated Swedish
words with German, English or French cognates and were asked to translate them into German. Half of
stimuli were presented visually; half of them aurally. Translation accuracy in the written modality was found
to improve sharply until age 30 and continues to gradually increase from that point onwards, whereas in
the spoken modality, translation accuracy reaches its zenith in middle age and starts to drop off around
age 50. The results furthermore indicate that these differing age patterns can be ascribed to a differential
reliance on cognitive resources in the two modalities. We discuss the impact of these cognitive resources
on receptive multilingualism as well as the implications of our findings for pedagogical approaches relying
on this type of interlingual inferencing.</content>
 </entry>
 
   <entry>
   <title>PhD thesis - Receptive multilingualism across the lifespan: Cognitive and linguistic factors in cognate guessing</title>
   <link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
   <updated>2014-02-27T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#phdthesis</id>
   <content type="html"> </content>
 </entry>
 
    <entry>
   <title>New article - The critical period hypothesis in second language acquisition: A statistical critique and a reanalysis</title>
   <link href="http://janhove.github.io/publications.html"/>
   <updated>2013-07-25T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://janhove.github.io/publications.html#cphreanalysis</id>
   <content type="html">In second language acquisition research, the critical period hypothesis (CPH) holds that the function between learners' age and their susceptibility to second language input is non-linear. This paper revisits the indistinctness found in the literature with regard to this hypothesis's scope and predictions. Even when its scope is clearly delineated and its predictions are spelt out, however, empirical studies–with few exceptions–use analytical (statistical) tools that are irrelevant with respect to the predictions made. This paper discusses statistical fallacies common in CPH research and illustrates an alternative analytical method (piecewise regression) by means of a reanalysis of two datasets from a 2010 paper purporting to have found cross-linguistic evidence in favour of the CPH. This reanalysis reveals that the specific age patterns predicted by the CPH are not cross-linguistically robust. Applying the principle of parsimony, it is concluded that age patterns in second language acquisition are not governed by a critical period. To conclude, this paper highlights the role of confirmation bias in the scientific enterprise and appeals to second language acquisition researchers to reanalyse their old datasets using the methods discussed in this paper. The data and R commands that were used for the reanalysis are provided as supplementary materials.</content>
 </entry>
 
</feed>
